Greetings again from Southern California.
My name is Joe Simpson Jr.
I'm a volunteer wrangler for
WordPress Accessibility Day,
I'm also a WordCamp WordPress Meetup
and WordCamp Community organizer
as well as an accessibility advocate.
Similar to Alicia's story
that we just heard in the last hour,
Sumner Davenport shaped my
re-entry into accessibility as well.
Now I know two people
in my entire life that are me.
I have a workout friend
who is always ready to go,
no matter rain or shine just like me,
no excuses.
Sumner is that other person.
She matches my desire to learn
with inspiration, knowledge
and nurturing leadership
here in the North Valleys of Los Angeles.
Now I met Sumner,
I went to a meetup in West Hills
to see her speak,
because I was hosting our first
WordCamp in Santa Clarita
and I had heard about her
and the topic was very interesting.
What happened at that meetup
is why I'm here before you today.
She's that type of magnetic personality.
She killed her presentation
and she said yes
and presented at our meetup
and we've been close ever since.
Sumner will present
The Profitability of Accessibility,
but first let me tell you more
about this amazing woman.
Sumner Davenport specializes
in web accessibility on WordPress.
Her passion is to educate business owners
and web designers using WordPress,
on the increased value and
ease of an accessible site.
Through her long-standing organization
she and her team have built, maintained,
evaluated and remediated,
dozens of WordPress websites
to WCAG 2.1 success criterion.
Her clients are referred by other clients
and from attorneys.
She's an active…
She's active in accessibility and legal
conferences and educational venues.
At WordCamps and local WordPress groups,
she regularly speaks on topics related
to compliance issues for WordPress.
After presenting at WordCamp
Santa Clarita in 2019,
[Joe silently mouthed "my meetup"]
she volunteered to be a speaker
wrangler at WordCamp Santa Clarita
and is on the speaker wrangler
team for WordCamp Los Angeles 2020.
She and two colleagues
founded a local meetup
to discuss WordPress and accessibility
and invited renowned speakers
on accessibility topics
to be guest presenters.
Partnering with two other
local meetup organizers
they organized the first
annual mega meetup
WordPress Accessibility Day 2020.
She is a member of the International
Association of Accessibility Professionals,
the IAAP,
and is an active supporter of
various disability organizations.
Please welcome Sumner Davenport presenting
The Profitability of Accessibility.
Sumner take it away.
I don't know
if I can talk after that introduction Joe.
Goodness, I'm glad I have my Kleenex handy.
You really touched me
with the beginning of that introduction.
Thank you so very very much.
I am very honored to be here tonight.
I am so glad that I was selected to speak.
Thank you so much to Joe Dolson
for putting this together,
and for saying yes to me
and of course, for Joe Simpson.
He is an inspiration to me a lot.
So I'm going to jump into my topic.
Let's see if I can get my
screen share to work here today.
If there's any problem hearing me,
if you have any problem with my screen,
make sure that you make a comment so
that one of the Joes here can let me know.
If you have any questions as I go along,
please put them in the chat
on the stream on YouTube,
so that Joe can let me know what those are,
because I want to be as
helpful as I possibly can
during the time that we have tonight.
So let's see if we can find my PowerPoint.
So the topic that I was
going to talk about tonight
is called
The Profitability of Accessibility
and I feel very honored that last night,
Joe Simpson took a few minutes to let
me do a kind of a test run on this topic.
And I made a little bit of an edit,
and then today another associate said,
hey let me hear what you're going to do
because I can't be there tonight.
So I did,
and after hearing what I had to say,
she kind of hemmed and hawed and
said hmm, I'm not thrilled with the title.
I thought well you know,
but the title is Profitability.
The profitability is the
degree to which a business
or activity yields a
profit or a financial gain.
Although accessibility—
bringing accessibility to all
persons is really the right thing to do,
it's important if this is what
you're doing professionally,
that you can make some money,
you can have an income,
you can thrive, so you can enjoy it.
So yeah, profitability.
So… I know, I thought
about it for a minute
and then she said, I
think it's all in the title.
I just don't like the title.
So based on her input, I changed the title.
So tonight, I didn't—
I did not warn Joe Dolson.
I already sent in my slides.
So I apologize if you are
following me on the slides online,
this next slide is not part of it.
Just one.
it's now called, Show Me the Money,
because isn't that what
people want to learn?
If you as a web designer,
as a business owner,
as an agency owner,
if you start to put your efforts
into including accessibility
and do all the projects
you do for your client,
don't you want to know
that there's a way that you
can get a return on investment
on your time and your efforts?
Well, I kind of figured
that was a better title
and for anybody that knows me, it
kind of sounds more like me as well.
So, tonight, we're going to talk about
how you can get a return
on investment on your time
and your efforts with accessibility
and how you can then also
have a good way to explain
accessibility to your clients,
so that they also can see
the return on investment
for bringing accessibility
into all of their digital products
and their company.
So first off, just of course, we all know
this, but we're just going to touch on it,
but what is accessibility?
Accessibility is removing the barriers
that prevent people from having access,
equal access.
whether it's a building, an area,
a service that's being provided,
a website, an app, any digital product.
And accessibility is taking that
initiative to create products
that are usable by,
with people, by people,
with the widest
possible range of abilities.
What some people may not know,
is when you think accessibility first,
and think about making things
accessible to all people,
you open so many avenues,
so many possibilities,
so much creativity and innovation,
that accessibility creates good growth
in a lot of ways.
And I'll touch on some of those tonight.
What is web accessibility specifically?
We have seen wA11y,
sometimes the W is not there,
it's just A11Y
and what that means is that
between the A and the y
there is actually 11 letters
that should be in there,
because it spells out the
entire word, accessibility.
We put the W in there for web.
So when you see wA11y or A11y,
whichever way you want to pronounce this,
it's accessibility.
It's about people.
It's about making a difference.
So web accessibility refers to the
website that is designed for everyone!
We want everyone,
regardless of their ability or disability,
to have the same ease of access.
That's the most important part.
It's the user experience
that everybody gets to have.
So we also have to keep in mind
that web accessibility,
it actually involves
a wide range of disabilities.
So many times we hear people
talk about only screen readers,
or blind individuals,
or somebody needing captions,
without taking into an understanding
that there are far more…
areas and ranges of disabilities
that we need to consider.
So then I get people that
say this to me all the time,
rather sarcastically,
they unfortunately do.
Is there really a need
for web accessibility?
I mean, after all, how many people
really are disabled?
I'm in the United States,
so some of the figures and facts
that I will present this evening
are based on my area.
But since this is global, I also
am going to show some figures
and I'll make comments on some
other countries as well.
Because accessibility is international.
In the United States, 25.6 percent
of adults in the United States
have some type of disability.
And that number fluctuates,
because there are disabilities
that individuals are born with,
there are disabilities that people suddenly
get because of an accident or an illness,
or surgery.
There's disabilities that come with age.
So that number is not just 25.6 percent.
It's really a fluctuating number that
could affect every single one of us.
Around the world, there
are more than one billion people
living with some form of disability.
So when someone says, is there
really a need for web accessibility,
is there really people that need it?
I kind of think there is.
I kind of think that it's important
that we take a look at what
I know to be an invisible
segment of our society.
When I ask people why
their site is not accessible
or why they don't consider accessibility,
they don't think they have
ever seen or know anybody,
but maybe that guy that just
passed him in the hallway,
that might have a disability.
They don't consider…
how many people they're overlooking.
It's an invisible segment of our society
that we need to bring visible.
And it's not them versus us.
It's not one group versus another.
It's all of us,
it's all of us collectively…
that make up this group.
People with disabilities
are in a community
that makes up a whole lot more
than just the single individual,
because it's their families,
their communities, their friends,
the people that they do business with,
the people that they interact with,
it's a very powerful consumer base.
And if a company has a website
and they're not accessible,
they're missing out on
this very powerful base.
So then the next question comes up.
Is there really a problem?
I mean after all, how big a
problem, if there is one, how big is it?
So for those of you that are familiar,
there's a company WebAIM,
and every year they do an audit
on the home page only,
of one million sites.
And for 2019, actually I correct myself,
February of 2020
they did their million sites evaluation
and what showed up was, 98.1%
of all the sites they tested had errors,
had barriers to people with disabilities.
Ninety-eight point one percent of
the sites they tested out of one million,
less than 2% were fully accessible.
And I've put on the screen
that big number because
I want people to see that number.
I want it to be important.
I want to let it be known
that there is an opportunity
for us as web designers
to make a difference.
It's a huge opportunity
and the source link to that
is at the bottom of the screen.
But are there other problems
with the lack of web accessibility?
I mean other than just
WebAIM's One Million report?
Absolutely.
Because of the lack of web accessibility,
we are seeing a drastic increase
in web accessibility lawsuits.
As Joe mentioned, I work with clients
who are referred to me by attorneys.
Since COVID started,
my phone, my email,
people contacting me because they've
received demand letters,
attorneys contacting me inquiring
about what can be done for their client.
It has tripled.
I can't handle all of these people.
But so far we're doing
a good job at either
working with them or referring them out,
but that is a huge increase just for me.
So this is not going to go away.
Whether it's COVID where people are now,
everyone is in their home
and relying upon the internet,
or whether it's going to be after Covid,
when it becomes real obvious
that everyone deserves
the right to equal access
everywhere, including the web.
And, personally, I appreciate
that there's attention being brought
to the lack of web accessibility,
I just don't care for these trolls at all.
So the more that we make
websites accessible,
the more these trolls…
is going to make their…
efforts more difficult.
And that's a goal of mine.
Here's an interesting piece of information
from the report from WebAIM.
The top six common types of WCAG 2
failures on these sites that they tested,
Look at this:
Low contrast text, 86.3 percent of pages
had low contrast text.
Earlier today there was a
presentation about colors and contrast.
So, hopefully, you attended
that particular presentation.
If not, when these videos are available,
I do hope that you go back and you watch
and listen to what Colleen had to say.
Right at the top, Low Contrast.
Personally, I don't understand why people
put gray font on a light gray background.
That's never made sense to me,
but I see that on so many sites,
and obviously WebAIM
found something similar.
The other one, Missing
alternative text for images, 66 %.
Come on, that's like the one
thing we talk about the most.
Empty links, Missing form
fields, Empty buttons,
Missing the document language?
We're not even going to tell people
what the language of the website is?
How easy if you had a website
that had these six errors,
they came to you, how easy would
it be for you to remediate that site?
Keeping that in mind, why aren't they?
That's my question.
Maybe they need you to knock
on their door and tell them.
Now, at the same time, I read
legal cases on a daily basis.
I always tell people if
you can't go to sleep,
something that's better than counting sheep
is to read some of these legal briefs.
They're not really entertaining,
but they are educational
and the most common problems
referred in these cases,
the website prevents screen readers
from accessing primary content.
Oh boy, here we go again,
no text description for an image,
forms not working,
you can't increase the text to 200 %
without loss of content or functionality?
Here's one that a lot of people
don't think about.
If you have something on your
website that has a time limit on it,
you need to let people
have a way to adjust it,
disable it, slow it down, restart it,
instead of just timing them
out and kicking them off.
Because a sighted person
would see if there's a countdown,
but perhaps someone
with a disability either
doesn't get the warning,
can't read the warning,
can't respond fast enough to the warning,
because you didn't give them enough time.
Web pages without titles,
oh my goodness.
It is so easy to put a
title in a WordPress site.
How could… how?…
I'm beside myself.
The purpose of each link cannot be
determined from the text link alone,
and that's where we get
a whole lot of those, "click here"
And I believe we had someone just
a couple of presentations previous,
that talked about just that.
Very, very important.
So you see that the problems
that are being referenced in lawsuits
and the ones that WebAIM found
are simple to remediate.
They're simple to put in the first place,
but when you have a client come to
you with a site that has these problems,
these are the
simple ones to fix.
So what's the solution
to the lack of accessibility?
Very simple, make products
that are accessible to everyone
out of the gate.
We do know that now that there are
themes within the WordPress repository
that are accessibility-ready.
I do know there are
people that, that's all they will work with
is an accessibility-ready theme.
And then they make sure
that the content and the images
and everything they add to it
remains accessible.
It makes their job easy.
Remediate products and areas
that have barriers,
support companies and products
that are accessible
and innovate with new products.
You may not have known,
that the disabled market
or excuse me, the disabled community,
is actually considered
to be extreme users of certain products.
What that means is,
what you may not also be aware of,
is that voice recognition software
has been available for people
with disabilities for 20 plus years,
and because people with disabilities
were using voice recognition technology,
that same technology is now used
in Alexa and Siri and Google's assistant.
So something that was done for a—
what was a select group of people
by their first analysis,
is something that has now
been rolled out for everyone.
So it's not a small group.
It's all of us that benefit
from these products.
But let's move in to what people
want to know about tonight
and that is, the Increased
Value of Accessibility
for both Designers and Companies.
What you hear a lot is,
accessibility can drive innovation,
such as what I just mentioned,
it can enhance your brand or hurt it.
It helps SEO,
it can minimize legal risk
and then it can extend your market reach.
And yet, those five points to some
people are just vague.
Yeah, maybe, but what about me?
What can it do for me, for my company?
or what can it do for me?
I'm a designer
with a small agency,
What can it do?
So look, I want to remind you,
if my slides will progress,
this market, 98.1% of
the market needs you,
for your web accessibility knowledge,
expertise,
to go in there and make a difference,
98%.
So when I hear people tell me,
well you know what, I… [sighs]
my client doesn't want to pay
for accessibility.
I don't know what to do?
Ninety-eight percent…
of the marketplace… needs you.
So if that client doesn't want
to be inclusive
and bring accessibility in
and you have done your
best to educate them,
maybe you need to turn your attention
to somebody who will appreciate you
and your skills, and your
commitment and your dedication.
Just saying.
But then we come back to,
well what can I charge?
You know I mean, I don't know,
how can I mark this up?
How do I make a living doing this?
When I first had a website made for me,
it was in 1996, 97-ish,
the person charged me $3, 000.
I didn't think anything of it
at the time, other than, phew,
that's a lot of money,
but I also thought that
must be the going rate,
because I had nothing
else to compare it to.
But the person that designed my website
was not very pleased,
because I kept asking questions
and I wanted this little
tweak and just that change,
and can we do this, and let's move that
and he made a statement one day
and said, look
I just don't have time for all your
questions. If you want answers,
go take a class
and get the answers for yourself.
So I did and I never had to
ask him another question,
but I also never had to
pay him any more money,
because I knew how then to do it myself.
So trust me, I never say that to clients,
but I look back at that and when I
first started working websites myself,
I knew I couldn't charge $3,000.
I didn't have that much intelligence,
expertise, information, experience,
even though I'd just taken a class.
I didn't think I could and I didn't.
So I came up with a value calculator
and here's where if you have
a pen or pencil handy
or you take notes on a notepad or
something, I'd like you to consider this.
When you think about what is your value
when you include accessibility
into your services,
what do you charge for a basic website
prior to adding any accessibility to it?
Put down that figure.
Now I want you to
consider your personal value.
If you have taken classes
on accessibility,
put a plus.
If you have certificates or degrees,
If you have any business
awards or accolades,
whether they're related to accessibility
or just because you have integrity
and you are a good business person
and you take care of your clients,
give yourself a plus.
If you are a disabled person yourself
or someone in your family
or a friend that you see often,
put a plus.
If you have employees
that are disabled that work for you,
put a plus.
If you have an understanding of WCAG,
for each level of understanding,
put a plus,
or a big plus.
If you are very involved in a particular
niche market that you know real well,
you know what the market is,
what drives them to do what
they do in their business, put a plus.
My niche market is attorneys.
It's been attorneys for
the last 10 and a half years.
So I know attorneys.
I know the legal marketplace,
I know what they're allowed to do
and what they're not allowed to do
when it comes to marketing
and advertising.
I am always networking with them.
So I know that market.
If you have a market like that,
give yourself a plus.
Give yourself a plus for every year
that you already have
been including accessibility.
If you can write code,
give yourself a couple of big pluses.
And if you often network with
other accessibility professionals,
give yourself a plus.
And then think about what else
sets you apart from everyone else.
That is a huge plus.
When you look at all those pluses you're
going to put a dollar amount to that,
not with me tonight,
but at a time when
you're going to sit down,
because this is something
that is personal to you.
Not what everybody else is charging,
but what is your value.
When you understand your value
you can explain it to your clients
and that's the important part.
So you start with that value,
then you go to something
where it requires manual efforts.
This is an excerpt, a clipping from one
of the checklists that we use in my office.
And it's a spreadsheet
that has on the left column
whatever action that we need to take
in order to remediate a site,
who's going to do that?
is that person someone that
works internal in my company
or do we have to outsource,
and what is the cost?
Every person that works on a project,
if they're internal,
they have either a salary
or a negotiated amount
that they are paid.
If we outsource it,
we are paying whatever
they tell us is their value
to do that for us.
We go down the list and we
make sure that we cover all our bases.
We do test everything on JAWS and NVDA
by a native user of that.
When we are remediating images,
we don't just…
throw in the alt description
and call it a day.
We research and maybe we
have to find them a new image
if the one that is on their site
is really not that great.
Maybe it needs editing,
because it's too pixelated,
maybe it's too big,
maybe it doesn't fit the content?
We're going to change the meta info
and the geo info for search
and we're going to do all that,
because we go the extra effort.
What we're doing for our client is more
than just fixing the technical problems,
we want a good user experience
for them as our client
and their website for their users
and their visitors.
So think about this type of an effort
and what value would
you put into each one of those?
How would you separate yourself
from everyone else?
A lot of times people
calculate an hourly rate.
I talked to someone this week
who told me—he came to me
and asked me if I'd hire him,
because he couldn't afford
to be freelance anymore.
So I looked at what he charged a client
to work on a website
And how many extra hours got
thrown in that he didn't calculate.
The end of the day, he was
making less than $7 an hour.
So in Southern California,
you can't live on that.
So I told him, if you're going to
calculate your value by an hourly rate,
ask yourself,
what is your resentment number.
What is the lowest amount you would ever
allow a client to say:
"This is how much I'll pay you per hour"
and take that number
and multiply it by four.
You should never work at a level
that causes you to not enjoy
the work that you're doing,
because accessibility
can be a whole lot of fun.
The people that you will meet,
the clients when they get excited,
it's just fun.
And then you have more value,
updates and maintenance plans.
In a lot of the settlements we're seeing
in these legal cases,
they're asking the court
to require that people
test their sites every six months.
That's a maintenance plan for you.
So that's how you add value,
that's how you add more to you.
Your total value then becomes
your unique value, your cost per hour,
your team that you work with,
the complexity of the site that
you're going to be working on,
and how well your skills
and expertise can do that,
the timeline—
rush jobs always cost more
and future offerings,
your updates and your maintenance plans.
Then you put that into a strategy.
When I first started
in business in the 80s,
long time ago,
I was out in my neighborhood
asking businesses,
why were they successful
and the guy next door wasn't?
Why did they continually succeed
when people across the street
kept going out of business?
And what I heard more times
from the successful business,
is they had a plan.
They didn't wing it.
They put in a plan and they planned it out
as far as they could.
They put in that plan,
not only the type of customers
and clients they wanted,
they put in that plan the type
of education they may need
in order to satisfy those clients,
they put in that plan
what would happen if
business really picked up?
So many people plan in the minute
and worry about something going wrong,
but as I said a couple seconds ago,
my phone calls and my emails have…
really exploded in the last few months.
Fortunately, I have a list of people
that I can call upon,
that I'm able to make sure
that those contacts
and those inquiries were taken care of.
Take the information about
your value, your expertise,
what kind of websites you want to work
on, and what you want to do,
and put it into a plan
and follow that plan.
Be transparent with your client
but don't be invisible.
What we do for our clients,
is we either work in Basecamp or Asana.
We work in Slack and Toggl
and we give our clients
reports all the time.
They know exactly
what we're doing for them,
so they don't have to worry.
And what we do,
is we audit their website
and we give them a report.
And we may audit that website
with an automatic tester,
before we put our hands on it
and manually test it,
and we will give them that report,
but then we make sure that they see
the difference it makes with
someone who is keyboard only,
and someone who is screen reader.
That way they get a better
understanding of their target market.
They get a better personal
understanding of accessibility.
I have been working with
accessibility and websites for 12 years,
maybe a little bit longer.
And I was brought to my knees humbly,
at that point.
I had been designing websites
and I thought I was doing a great job.
And I thought I was really
proud of what I had,
and then a member of
my family, who is blind,
had the benefit of someone coming
to show her how to use a screen reader
to access the web and visit websites.
I was emotionally blown away
by how much freedom it gave her,
but I also was humbled when I gave the
man my URLs of the sites I was so proud of
and asked him to test them.
And not a single one of them…
could be read by a screen reader.
My world changed that day.
And so I'm hoping that as you
get accustomed to accessibility,
your world takes a shift
and you shift to where this just
becomes part of what you do,
don't even have to think about it.
So after you get the test and
you find out what you're doing
and you start working with your client,
please do the easy stuff first.
and the reason for this is,
if you are working on the
most difficult part of the website
where you possibly have to write
some new code
and redesign certain things,
your client doesn't see what you're doing.
He doesn't see that you're making
any sort of progress at all,
but if you go through the little things
first or what I call the easy things,
not little, they're all important,
the easiest things first and then
show your client as you go along.
Your client sees progress.
Your client sees hope
and knows that you're doing
what you'd promised to do.
We always follow the WCAG, the checklist.
I have this spreadsheet on the screen
that shows the guidelines and
where they fall under WCAG.
In all of our spreadsheets we reference
not only with internally to
each other, but to our clients,
which web content accessibility guidelines
success criteria we are meeting for them.
They don't care,
but they do care
that we tell them.
They don't understand it, but
they care that we tell them
and that's the transparency of it.
And that's what's important.
Plus when you follow the WCAG,
you learn the WCAG.
When you do this, the simple stuff first
you learn. It's easier to learn.
So basically you can have an
increased profit with your business
by increasing your value to your client,
increasing the fees that
you're going to charge them,
because of the value of what
you're bringing to the table.
This will increase your business income
and unless you go out
and buy a brand new Ferrari,
it should be an increase in your profit.
But I want you to notice that
one thing I didn't say,
I didn't talk about plug-ins
as part of this process,
because it's good, bad
and ugly with WordPress.
The good is there's plugins
that can do work for you.
The bad is, a lot of those plugins
will make the site worse
and you're now going to have
to figure out how to remediate
over the plugin that
you just installed.
And the ugly is that there are plugins
that through their marketing efforts
are going to try to tell you
that they'll do your job for you.
And then when they don't,
you're the one that's in trouble.
So don't be the bad apple.
Be willing to put in the effort.
You will enjoy it,
you'll get excited, trust me.
Now we'll get to the second half
and I promise
that this is a good part of it that
you'll be able to share with your clients.
The Profitability for Companies.
People with disabilities
are not a solitary market.
They are surrounded by family
members and friends.
They recognize products and services
that accommodate people in society.
They will refer to people
when it is an accessible website.
So you want to show
them the money.
In the U.S., the total after-tax
disposable income for working age people
with a disability is 490 billion dollars.
That's a lot of money.
Discretionary income which is
the income that they get to spend
after they've paid all their debts
and their taxes is still 21 billion.
Most people aren't aware of these numbers.
You want to share these with your clients.
Interesting note that we discovered,
is that individuals
with hearing difficulties
represent the disability category with the
greatest amount of discretionary income,
followed by people
with vision disabilities.
So when you heard about captions
from Meryl earlier today
this shows why that's important.
You can explain that to your clients.
If you're in the UK,
what we have there is,
internet users are 10.7 million
or 10.07.
Sixty-nine percent
of people will leave a site
if they have a problem with access
and they will go someplace else.
This is called the Click-Away Pound report
and in my resources I do have a link
that you can read this entire report
and share it with your clients.
I also have a Nielsen report
that gives all the information
for US companies,
but the worst case scenario
that you can tell your clients
is that the cost of a
lawsuit is far greater.
An attorney retainer
can be up to $5,000,
the settlement costs, the loss of work.
Those are real figures
and I do not lead with this
with my clients.
I lead with the numbers for
the market that they can reach.
If they don't want to listen,
then I'll bring this part in.
But how should they market
to the disabled community?
Besides developing products that
meet the needs of people with disabilities.
They should get involved in the community.
They also need to employ
people with disabilities.
Inclusive advertising,
put an accessibility statement
on their website,
because far too
many designers think,
well I'll just go in and tell my client
if they make their website accessible,
that people will flock to it.
That's not true.
It will give a boost to the SEO
in some cases,
but they still need to do their marketing.
It's essential and this is the type
of marketing that they need to do.
If they do this marketing,
if they do it genuine,
they will see a return
of that marketplace,
because like any other community,
people with disabilities do talk
about people that treat them right.
And when you think about
your price and your value
just remember there's always somebody
who's willing to do it cheaper.
So don't cut yourself short
when you're talking
to your clients about your value.
Make sure that you go for the big value.
So some of the references
or resources that I'll share with you,
is the automatic accessibility
checkers that we use.
We don't use one more than another
except, the top two.
We love the Deque axe Pro beta,
because of the type of reports
that we can give our client
and we love the Tenon API
which you can put in your website,
so that you can see as you're working,
what you're doing and
what needs to be done.
So you don't have to wait till
something is done to go, did I do it right?
By putting the API on your website for this
one, you'll be able to watch your progress
and learn as you go along.
Other resources that I mentioned, these
are places where you can learn knowledge:
The Web Accessibility Initiative at w3.org
has a free course on the
introduction to web accessibility,
and you can get a certificate
for completing that course
and it is a great course.
I've done that course.
I refer people to that course.
It's full of knowledge.
Knowbility, excellent resource,
Deque, WebAIM, CSUN,
University of Illinois,
University of Washington,
the information is available.
The educational resources are there.
If you need to have a native user to test,
here are three places where you can have,
you can contract with them
for someone or gain a referral.
Again, Knowbility AccessWorks,
Pearson for the Blind and CSUN
which is here in Southern California.
Also in my slides will be the
links and resources to the statistics
that I quoted for the companies,
for the number of people in the
community and the spending power.
So, in summary, 98.1% of websites
need remediation.
One in four people
have a recognized disability.
Accessibility is international.
It's a right, it's a personal right,
it's a civil right.
Plan your design to include accessibility,
have a strategy for remediation,
understand the why and
how of your value to a client,
understand the potential market
so you can explain it to your client.
Check the obvious and fix those first—
fonts, structure, color
schemes, video, audio.
Don't rely only on automatic testers.
Test your site manually.
Have a native user of accessibility
technology test your site.
Be transparent with your clients
and support the community.
And I know I talked fast.
I wanted to give you a lot of information
and since I know we're being recorded,
you can come back
and visit this information again.
But I do believe if there are questions,
maybe I have a couple minutes
to answer questions.
Yes you do, thank you so much Sumner.
What a great presentation, thank you.
All right, let me refresh here.
Our first question  is:
Is there a study answering
the following question:
How many people leave a web page
because of accessibility failure?
Sixty-seven percent.
It's in the Click-Away Pound report.
Okay
And the report also indicates
that when people leave that website,
they don't give up,
they do spend that money elsewhere.
So it's a total loss.
All right, do you feel designer and
developer reluctance
in folding in accessibility
is that they undercharge
or overestimate their bottom line?
How would you recommend they address
this or can you share a brief experience?
My recommendation would be that they
go through that list
of what I did for value
and accept…
more about what their
personal value is as a designer.
And if they've
undervalued themselves,
this is probably a personal issue
that they need to take and look at.
And they might want to
sit and work with someone.
I sit with designers all the
time that want to discuss,
how can I increase what I charge?
I don't know what my assets are?
So if a person will take a list of
what are their personal assets,
like the list I rang off
and then reevaluate.
What does happen, is many times they
don't charge enough, they get burned out.
And then it becomes resentment
and that doesn't work,
but at the same time
whatever amount they charge
you don't want to overcharge because you're
going to have to live up to that amount.
All right, next question,
do you think that web
development is driven too much by
developers needing
to rapidly solve problems
defined by business rather than by users?
Not sure if I understand that question.
Okay, let me, let me restate it.
Do you think that web development
is driven too much
by developers who are trying to solve
business related problems
instead of trying to solve the problem
in terms of how a user would use it?
So if I understand that correctly,
a client's going to come to
a designer and say
I need a website built,
because I need to sell a product,
instead of I need a website
built that's the best
for user experience so
I can get more business.
Correct
Okay, well yeah, clients don't know.
We have to educate them.
That's what they need from us.
They need us to say,
"hey, you know what, that's great"
let me help you understand how we
can make that dream of yours even bigger
and more profitable.
So we as designers need
to also be educators.
Once we understand it, we can explain it.
All right, this is a really brief one,
For the non-legal,
what is a demand letter?
You mentioned that in your presentation.
What does that mean in
relation to accessibility?
Demand letter is… [laughs]
it's actually a form letter unfortunately,
but it comes in on an attorney letterhead
and it says dear website owner
I'm sending you this letter
because my client, a blind user,
or a person with another disability,
attempted to visit your website
and there was barriers that
prevented this person from equal access.
So it's important that you
contact our office to discuss
some form of remuneration
for the difficulties
and the problems that
my client has endured.
And that is the precursor
to them filing a case.
They send out the demand letter,
because they want someone to call and go
"please, please please"
and beg that you don't hurt them.
When most of those demand
letters don't turn into cases,
but many of them do.
In either case,
it's important to consult with
an attorney how to respond.
Awesome. Okay our final question is,
[coughs]
excuse me,
if you build a website
with accessibility in mind
and the same site without it
what do you think the difference in cost
would be between the two sites
in terms of what you can charge?
Uh, hmm
That's a difficult question.
I'm not sure...
Well, I don't know that I can answer it,
because if I go back to
when I was building sites
before I knew anything about accessibility
and I know what I charge then,
versus what I charge now,
I don't know how I would back out
all my accessibility efforts
to try to figure out
what that would be.
I'm just asking—
Yeah, I was going to
say I wouldn't, I mean
I can't even figure that out.
Yeah, that's a difficult question.
[Sumner laughing]
It reminds me, I used
to speak at high schools
or go to the school when they
had the parents come to work
and there would always be a kid who
would say, how much do you make?
which is…
I mean it's a random question.
I'm not making fun of it, but
it's a difficult question to quantify,
because your value is based
on that formula you talked about.
Exactly and too many times I see
in forum posts and discussion groups
where someone will say, well okay I'm going
to build a five-page website for a client,
what would you charge?
Well first off that's
not enough information
to find out what that price would be,
but on the other hand don't
choose somebody else's number.
Your value and their value
are totally different
and I really believe that when we get
into that thinking pattern where we say,
what is it I'm bringing to the table here?
And be real clear of what
I'm bringing to the table
has a big value to this client,
because no one else is
bringing this same value.
And I'm going to make
a difference to this client
and their website and the user experience
that no one else is going to
do, because they're not me.
And it's not ego, it's confidence.
Great, well thanks again Sumner,
what are you up to in the next few weeks?
or what can we look forward
to hearing from you with?
Well, I've got a lot of speaking
engagements, it seems,
you know since we're not traveling
the country or the world right now.
Everybody's on Zoom.
So I have a lot of that, and
we're planning for a next meetup
that's coming up that we're
going to do another hands-on.
We have the WordCamp Los Angeles
that's coming up in a couple of weeks.
So there's a lot still going on.
Awesome, well thanks again for sharing
with this incredible international audience
and I know we appreciate it.
For people that want to—for,
I didn't—sorry,
I didn't mean to interrupt, Joe,
but for people that want to follow
me I'm Sumner Davenport on Twitter,
I'm Sumner Davenport on LinkedIn
or please go to the meetup and look
for the WordPress San Fernando Valley.
And since we're on Zoom, you can
come in from anywhere in the globe
and participate and contribute
and let's all learn together.
How can I be so rude
and not let you lean on that.
[Sumner laughing]
All right thank you again, Sumner.
Thank you, Joe.
All right I personally like to thank
Joe Dolson for his leadership,
I'd like to thank my moderators
Zsolt Edelényi
and Danang Aprias Noor Fadilla
and all the volunteers and organizers
who made this incredible event possible.
As it continues on, make sure you check in
for our next presentation
who's going to be hosted
by Robert Remedios.
He'll introduce our next talk
called Gutenberg Accessibility,
a Screen Reader User's Perspective
with Raghavendra Satish
at five o'clock UTC
on this same channel.
See you there and we'll
be back after a short break.